Paul Williams of New Zealand is the man in the middle today taking charge of his second match at his Rugby World Cup.
Two old adversaries draw swords inside the greatest rugby playing arena of them all.
George in the red kicked us off.
We've just listened to the Portuguese fans already.
Match with a high testing box kick.
Lost forward, Apresidze has it to his halfback partner Abjadadze.
The youngest man ever to play it fly off in a Rugby World Cup.
Apresidze in his 50th game for Georgia to Mamoukashvili who has over 100.
Oh, Gigaashvili stealing through the middle.
Just shackled by a Portuguese trap.
Georgia begin to move this wide.
Niniashvili, Todawa the 36 year old to Saki Nadze.
His first game since June after a troublesome injury.
Nadiashvili, 53 year old, gnarled, loose head.
Abjadadze to Krasiladze who is rocked by that shot.
Quick ball for Georgia, Abjadadze, Gigaashvili shoveling it on.
Niniashvili's in the line, what a pass!
Tabutsadze's away!
The Georgian Globetrotters have arrived in Toulouse.
What a statement from Georgia.
And their sharpest tool Akaki Tabutsadze, the record triscorer.
Splinters the deadlock inside 90 seconds.
Well it was clinical stuff.
Side line to side line, the big men doing their job.
Spilled ball there.
And that gave the men in red an opportunity.
You can see Nathan Korsh just asking for help.
Look he's calling, we need more men out here, we need more men.
And in the end they did because there were too many red jerseys lined up.
Look at this sublime offload. Out the back door.
A beautiful and a perfect start for Georgia.
30th try and 34 tests for Akaki Tabutsadze.
Abjadadze slots the extras.
Georgia 7, Portugal 0.
Statement made.
Well as you see there's just not enough white jerseys.
Great footwork there to step out of the initial tackle.
And the presence of mind, keep that ball alive.
Nice and early.
Great stuff and Rob that's daunting if you're a Portuguese fan.
Alright, staggering start.
Gotta say tactically Georgia rewritten the script.
Last week against Australia it was 2.7 kicks to passes.
They've already played more rugby than we saw last week.
Incredible start from them.
Scrum half for Georgia closes.
Rugby in Montpellier, not too far from here.
Top 14 winner a year ago.
Portela responds.
Rene Ashvili architect of that Tabutsadze try.
Looking for a 50-22.
Ninos who's against gets back in time.
He's a nifty customer as well.
Rene Ashvili.
Throws the ball down the tram lines.
Was that a 50-22? Not quite.
It's awkward from Portugal.
March puts Portela in all sorts of trouble.
And George and Ransack them at the base.
Knock on advantage to the Ninos.
They too cough it up.
Portugal being caught in some Georgian traps at the moment.
Well credit to Georgians, they got downfield here.
A little bit careless, the pass is low.
Thought he had more time than he did.
Good pressure, downfield.
From the Georgian fullback.
Ashvili, and it won't be the last time he calls his name.
He looked for the offload, couldn't quite come off.
But not a strong start from this Portuguese outfit.
Space imbalance.
The width that Georgia are looking to play with.
Befits a team who really are coming out to make a statement.
They're playing wide, they're running with real power and pace in these outside tunnels.
It's going to be difficult for Portugal unless they up their defence.
And Rob, they add that to this component of the game.
The Scrimmagingues we're going to see here.
World renowned obviously.
The Georgian coach will be so happy with that.
Ashvili, he knows this element of the game, Scrimmaging.
But he's trying to add the other element so they can win and compete.
If there was one complaint, they got that loss against Australia.
As you noted, they just didn't have the width and the multi-dimension to their game.
Lajuske already frustrated.
Understandable.
Five penalties given away by Portugal at Scrim time against the Welsh.
This would be an area the Georgians will look to not just strangle,
they'll look to actually keep hold of it throughout.
Both sides in.
Good side.
You two are excellent.
Excellent.
You two, not good.
More space please.
Here's your mark.
There's the front of the report card issued early doors.
A very experienced set of players in there.
Nari Ashvili, Mamouk Ashvili, Gigashvili, all over 30.
Francisco Fernandes on the lucid side with the mop of hair.
The right of your pictures, 38 years old.
Right, Tager, 34.
He's going to be very good for it.
They've got the two shirts.
This is the game.
The aspect of play that Georgia have built their name on.
Apresidze to Abzhandadze.
Taboud Sadzi off his line when he's wrapped up in a big shot by Nicola Martins.
Apresidze to Gorgadze.
Apresidze.
Nari Ashvili.
Took a year out of rugby to deal with some problems with his knee and his ankle.
But he's back at 33 in another Rugby World Cup.
Apresidze to Abzhandadze.
Options shot down outside him.
He went it alone.
Yeah, yeah, he's lost it.
Coach Gloamal stole it back.
Mamouk Ashvili.
Played all over England and France.
Now back in Georgia.
Gignashvili to Janahonia.
Grangey blindside flanker.
Faces mounting for Georgia.
Chris Eladze on his 50th.
Last fight here.
Janahonia stepping but can't get away from Diogo Hasfaraira.
Mikhail Khadze.
Into double figure face count here.
Sharik Khadze to Ninashvili who's almost shadow boxing with Portela.
Neither man able to land a killer blow.
Big penalty for Portugal.
Oh, and the two nines are going at it.
A couple of meerkats jousting in amongst the big boys from the French plains.
Well, these sides won't back down. Listen to this.
Well, Samuel Marques had right to be more dependent.
That man there, he was looking for the ball.
I hope he's going to have a little chat here. Let's listen to him.
Then red nine pulled into the four which started it.
And he's advanced it ten if you want, but it's red nine who caused the issue.
Yeah, I think so.
Here you go boys.
That's it. Three power Williams.
Red nine has actually stopped them from being able to go quickly.
So we're going to advance the penalty.
And listen, just while we're here, we don't need any more of that, okay?
It stops now.
These teams do battle every single year.
They are the fiercest of rivals. They're the two strongest teams.
Tom's going to go back on.
Which sits beneath the six nations.
I wonder that the two smallest blokes on the field, those two pesky scrum halves,
the heart of the tummels.
But let's not forget that penalty came as a reward for good Portuguese defence.
He started out, here he wants to go quickly and that's his right.
He's lucky he doesn't have a yellow there actually because he's prevented some action.
And Portugal need to play with up tempo.
If I was the Portuguese skipper, I'd be planting that seed in referee Williams' head and say,
hey, don't let them take this game away from us.
Scrappy line-out ball for Portugal.
But they do have their first meaningful possession of the match.
Match.
Portela, off of the corner.
Covered by Nini Ashwini.
Oh, hold!
He chases.
George will fly off all the way back.
Portugal want this to go dead.
And it does.
Scrum back from where Nini Ashwini kicked it.
And from a dazzling assist.
To an over-kicked kick.
Well, perhaps a cruel first bounce.
This is the stadium to lose.
Not the home of Stad.
It is the soccer home.
So it's a little bit firmer than the Eastern.
This ball just takes off.
A bit cruel there.
It will be a great turn of events for the Portuguese.
Just look at the distance that is kicked there.
Understandably, heading home.
But that's just outside his 22.
If that did go into the 22, it would have been George's ball.
A real tactic for both of these teams is to kick territorially.
They like to kick long.
And they've got some absolute power in these legs as well.
Portugal's attack feels beautifully against the Welsh.
And really impressed with ball in hand.
They love to give it some air to use the expansive,
dangerous players in their back line.
There's Match.
Portela, plenty of options.
And he hits one of them, it's put on court.
Release now, Tecla.
Good roll, good roll.
Match holding it up well for Jose Madeira.
Match just loses it.
It didn't go backwards.
Advantage.
And then it went forward and George is staffing it back.
Got the advantage of the knock-on.
Yeah, he's taken it there.
That's really trascor of against Australia.
Former soldier.
Former soldier in the Georgian army.
Only took up rugby about 10 years ago in his early 20s.
The recommendation of a friend.
Dragged him along to training.
Here is Big Beck at 30-odd caps later.
She's against.
Knocks it forwards.
Just a knock-on.
He was never going to be able to react to that.
Nice bit of refereeing there.
It went forward off a white player's hand.
And caught by another white player.
But as he said, no time to react.
It's not going to be a penalty, which would have been an option there.
Not much that Stotti having knocked it on could do there.
Just to explain the kicks recently.
This is really interesting stats when we look at it.
Georgia against Australia had 2.7 kicks per pass.
That means they didn't have up to three passes before they kicked it.
Already we've seen the impact of these.
The high boxers, as it's known, tactically and territorially working well for them so far, Georgia.
Yeah, Georgia kicked 55 times in the open round of fixtures.
They're not going to beat any team besides England.
The average are around 25 kicks per game in the Rupert Europe Championship.
They like to put boot to ball and use that mighty pack to get them in the right areas of the pitch.
Penalty advantage to Georgia.
Abzandadze front-football for Kweśeladze.
Ninny Ashvili puts the hammers down.
Tabudzadze gets back to his feet.
Abzandadze inside.
Ninny Ashvili climbs on.
I don't think so, mate.
Fabulous rugby from the Georgians.
But there was a little fumble.
Paul Williams wasn't sure.
The ball is in the red and it attacks the white player.
Chris Busby helping him out with the far side assistant referee.
Knocked on.
Georgia weaving some lovely stuff.
Well, Portugal had faulted.
Their line speed is really poor. They're not coming forward.
As a result, they have to receive this pressure and some good hard running.
No substitute for that.
From the Georgians in their back, they sit themselves up here.
Just a slight knock on there.
The assistant official has seen it and radioed it in.
What a luxury it is for these backs to be able to build a house upon the rocks.
Because this scrum is so incredibly solid from Georgia.
You know you can get your set piece nailed.
Your backs moves can flow on the back of it.
75% of the opening 12 minutes.
Georgia possession.
Portugal scarce they had a sniff.
They will have a preview with this free kick.
So that's a free kick. The Georgians not listening to the referee's commands.
They will have a meeting before him.
And a quick tap and go.
It's unorthodox but he wheels it in.
Holding red!
The rookie of the year in 2022.
We've all seen what he can do.
Ball in hands.
Yours is opposite man, Suza Gij.
He'll feel the bite.
He stays inside.
It's 22.
Portela keeps it in.
Father, one of the 2007 contingent.
Miguel Portela.
Red!
Portugal are now treading.
And Ninni Ashwili can pick his spots.
The pounce of the pops so cruel for him.
Acres of unguarded Toulouse real estates.
But March Cap make much distance with his own clearance.
That's clever play from David Ninni Ashwili.
Yeah, I just noted it.
There's no one back there to cover after the bit of the kicking duel.
And actually not that well executed kick.
You don't want to be the old guy.
When some people are talking about the role of the spiral kick to get it to pick up and roll.
And that shows the dominance from this Georgian team.
With ball in hand.
Six canes from Portugal.
Feeding off scraps.
And Georgia.
With this big lead tank.
And motoring.
Portela at the back for Port Gadset.
And Gadset.
Gadset.
Makes a couple more meters.
Gadset again.
Too long prop.
The European Challenge Cup winner.
Portugal infringing at the base.
So, Merab Shariq Gadset, the captain.
Trundles further.
Abzandadze.
It's going to be Toroa to get after that.
But it's never likely to get hold of it.
And we will go back for the Portuguese infringements.
Yeah, going back for the penalty at the breakdown.
I think it was Granada who just got on the wrong side.
And didn't get out of the way.
Wasn't rolling away.
And that became material because Georgia couldn't recycle the ball.
Let's watch here.
This is after these big hits coming in from both sides.
There he is, wrong side.
He's got to get out of there a bit quicker.
And the scrim half is maybe holding him in there.
And that's the one.
Material.
Here we are.
I haven't shot.
I shot Corgot.
Pointing to the posts.
Trying to turn this pressure into points.
Well, as you mentioned off the top, this is one of the great rugby cities in the world.
This is the football stadium.
But our drone giving us some incredible shots.
A sellout here.
And that's the game for all the French.
Obviously, Georgia and Portugal.
But their love of the game, their knowledge of the game.
They've already had the wave going.
And it's really what World Cups are all about.
Coming to venues like this.
And the incredible support the French have given right across the country.
The first George and fly half.
To play in the French top 14.
Over 300 points for this country now.
And he adds another three.
Georgia 10, Portugal 0.
The St George cross is not just for England.
Georgia will want to build on this.
A strong start. 16 minutes in.
Interesting they took the three.
They're going to keep that scoreboard ticking over.
Rob, I'm not sure what you take is in that.
Yeah, very much a case of them trying to get these possessions they've got down in pointscoring.
Portugal haven't really been down in the Georgia territory to score.
They might get a chance here.
It's all very untidy.
Ninny Ashveili is in a dark old corridor.
And Stevie Cerchera envelops him in his octopus-like arms.
And then he doesn't roll away.
It's hard to get out of the way when you're 6 foot 10.
Arms and legs everywhere from big Stevie Cerchera.
But he's got to get out of the way.
And he's got to get out of the way.
Arms and legs everywhere from big Stevie Cerchera.
But, George, I have to jail here.
Yeah, he's deemed not releasing there.
I thought the Georgian player may have taken an extra roll.
Which makes it hard.
But it will be a penalty to Georgia.
Again, a chance for him to calm down, clear the lines and look at this stadium.
This was the tackle.
Off the kickoff, loose ball.
Georgia will want to clean this up.
They look for a second like Portugal might have a run in.
The tackle comes in here.
There's the hard tackle and there's one roll.
And the second roll by the Georgian.
Not much big Stevie can do to get out of the way.
Love the throw to the tail from Mamoukashvili.
Abshantadze at the back for Sharikadze and Kveseladze.
Pierce's the Portuguese defence.
A placida for Gagashvili.
Gagashvili takes some stopping.
They pull that line side with Nini Ashvili in the line again.
Gagashvili is coming through a mountain of early work.
And they're up to five carries.
Nini Ashvili holds it up.
Janahonya galloping away.
Didn't give the pass but does now.
And might not be given.
It is.
Nini Ashvili pounces on the loose ball.
It's Apracidze in fact.
He grounds it.
We just need to check.
By red into a white player.
And then went forward.
If there was a knock on in the lead up.
The referee thinks he's seen it clean.
He's not going to have a look. He hasn't signalled up to the TMO.
In our crew here.
I must admit I thought it came off the chest.
And maybe having a look here.
TMO are trying to help him out.
They're having a look in there.
That's it.
The TMO will just sweep this up in the background.
Whether or not Paul Williams signals for the TMO review.
Which he is doing now.
All these incidents are always monitored by our officials on slightly ground.
Now we're going to take a more formal look at things.
Portuguese fans gave a relief.
There when the signal came in.
And there's Joy Neville.
Here's your first angle.
Clearly comes off the right arm.
Of the right arm.
Of the red player.
Clearly a knock on.
Yeah I agree.
OK thank you. Back to me.
OK. So no try.
Knock on.
It's gone wide.
The night of trying is 50th outing for Georgia.
And the only reason they're in that position is an incredible try saving tackle.
Just before this.
As they bust through the line.
Sosa gets his last man back.
Big powerful running.
From the back row forward.
He decides to keep it.
And look at the cover coming for the demeanour.
It's the fly half actually.
Corrections.
What a tackle. And that saved 7 points for Portugal for sure.
The concern is how they're defending out wide.
Because they've got no line speed.
The defenders on the outside are getting in front of the ball.
And that means those short lines are happening all day.
It's exactly how Georgia scored the first try.
And to be fair that probably should have been another one as well.
Yeah Rod.
The Portuguese slowly come up in defence.
They're receiving the tackle.
And they're getting caught behind the game line.
Making life easy for the Georgians.
Big scrum here.
Backed up 10 minutes from the long line. Portugal.
One more.
The squeeze comes on from the Georgian pack.
But quickly away from Simoes to Appleton.
Squeeze the way out of the desperate position.
Appleton stragged at the base.
Portugal struggling to resource these rucks.
To get Potties in there.
And to put four or five in there.
To get rid of Chalva Mamacachvili and his big calls.
And Portela under pressure.
Steers a decent kick away.
Tabudzadze keeps it alive.
Ninashvili, what does he have up his sleeve? Delving into that box of tricks and that on inside ball was on again.
It just slipped out of the palm and Max chases Ninashvili all the way back.
He's just doing shuttle runs up and down the pitch just now, the George and Fulback.
He picks his spot.
A little trickle into touch.
And Rob, it's interesting, the Portuguese forwards are actually holding up okay at scrum time,
but just not quite sure how much energy they're exerting because they don't seem to be up and off their feet.
They're getting caught in situations like this.
I think that's exactly it. It's an eight-man effort in these scrums at the moment,
which I know sounds like a simple comment, but when Portugal are exerting all that energy to just keep parity,
the Georgians are round the corner far quicker. It's a real nuance,
but just watch how much more mobile the Georgian forwards are at the moment.
Portuguese line-out pinched.
Gorgadze for Avshan Dadze.
Now Shaddy Kadze splits the Portuguese line with a clever kick.
Storti in trouble. Tabot Sadze wraps him up.
Storti keeps it alive, but the flag does go up from Chris Busby.
And Akaki Tabot Sadze takes the acclaim.
It's 1-0 in the battle of the winners.
Rafael Storti didn't think he was in touch there,
but maybe just a little bit guilty of trying to make something happen.
They had a little bit of possession there, and he wanted to do something,
but he's put his team in trouble.
Guys, guys.
Time off, time off, time off.
Shalva-Namakashvili's beard.
Look out, Toma. Quickly.
Put him on the minutes.
Guys, the ball was actually still in play. He wasn't in touch.
So we've made a mistake.
We're going to restart with a scrum, your ball, Akaki, because you're in position.
Yep.
It's going to be a scrum, guys. He wasn't in touch.
Everybody's human, even the referees.
Rafael Storti not quite over the touch line.
These replays will show us.
Just get rid of that ball in the nick of time.
Because Portugal are in possession, they will have the put in at the scrum.
That's it, we'll restart.
Well, just backing up that there are actually four sets of eyes plus on what's going on out there.
Don't see that that often, but it will mean Portugal still have possession.
The poor old Portuguese put up the scrumage again.
It's a great opportunity to see exactly what we're talking about now.
The amount of effort going in from these Portuguese forwards,
I think is seriously going to tell in the latter stages of this game.
Cracks!
Nice, sir.
Bound!
The leg and back muscles of Portuguese forwards who are already screaming in pain and they go early.
And that's often the case when the opposition pack is dominant.
Hit and chase.
Scrum again, surely.
I'm so worried about the power of the Georgian pack.
They preempt the hits and unsurprisingly, Georgia are going to put them through the heart arena again.
I think 90% of the stadium knew that call was coming. Georgia want the scrum.
I don't think even the Portuguese forwards backed up.
I do enjoy the fact the referees try and coach the sprung row in this situation.
Better than how many thousands of scrums they've been in.
The 38-year-old Paul Williams and Teranaki.
The scrum half of his time.
Quite exponent of the dark arts in the front row.
He stood beside me.
Advantage, pulling back.
Georgia got a free shot there.
Fennaty advantage.
Tabutsahtse into Krasilantse.
What a collision that was in midfield.
Apresente for Burgadze.
Martins claims on, holds him down.
But it's front foot ball with every carry for Georgia.
Gigas really tackled off the ball.
Paul Williams will bring them back for the scrum penalty.
In that final phase there may have been an early tackle but we were on.
Advantage, as he said, from the scrum penalty, pulling back.
It's the interpretation.
So still more possession.
Back and down.
No you don't.
This was the midfield.
He looks to the right, there's an early tackle there.
The ball actually hits him in the head.
And he's got the ball.
And Gigas really wasn't happy there.
Could have been another penalty.
Should have been.
Portugal.
Went for the Jamala.
Pambas plays red.
And there is a statement of intent from Georgia.
Sex with the colt.
Not content with three points.
They want five or seven.
Portugal trying to compete.
Martins nearly gets there but it's Chachanize who wins it.
And this is where Georgia can turn on the power.
Portugal stand up to that physical assault so well.
But there's more work to do.
Last fight, what?
This is Chachanize from Micaltaze.
They continue to keep it tight.
Gigas Vili felled on the five meters line.
Francisco Fernandez, what a tackle.
The 38 year old war horse.
With the bushy hair.
Sticks that big head in the spokes.
And the oldest man on the pitch comes up with a precious, precious penalty.
Yeah they pound it away but look at the guy here.
That ball's not on the floor so it's not a rock.
He has rights to get his hands on it and he does.
Fantastic work from the man who plays this club, Rugby at Bezier.
That's probably a difference to this Portuguese side robin last few years.
So many of these big men playing the rugby at the likes of Bezier, Pepe Gnall, Dax in France here playing good quality rugby.
So their forwards aren't sort of overly impressed by the quality of Georgia.
There's something that Lattice said at the start of the game.
He was talking about the fact this is the strongest squad they've ever had together.
The clarity of the clubs to be able to release the players.
He set out a four year plan and it's very much coming to fruition.
Very much not coming to fruition but Pernodino Portela makes a pretty kick with those prongs.
Jose Madera.
This was an itch.
Boot on Coor.
It's awkward.
Thank you.
Triple and rubber kick for Ninashvili.
Scoops it up well.
Gets through the boot on Coor.
Gets red off Stortie.
Look at Ninashvili go.
Gets it away to Kviseladze.
Martins with the tackle.
Ninashvili gets a boot to it.
And it's out on the full but wow.
Just enjoy the fluidity.
The wonderful motions of Davide Ninashvili.
Well he just backs himself at every turn.
He had no right stepping away from those two defenders.
Beautiful pass.
Then almost gets it back again.
Knowing him.
Surprised this didn't stay on the park.
The little chip ahead.
It's so dangerous.
Anyone that thinks that George is just a side that can scrimmage.
Look again.
This is a complete 15 side.
Portugal might be winning by now.
But it's taking every ounce of energy.
Every inch of space.
She's to get the ball back in their hands.
For the Wendish.
Okay done now.
Last feet guys.
Onside.
Chases here.
Use it there Nine.
Well that's charged down by Mikael Tadze.
And the right back where we started.
Let's go.
There he is.
Top.
Top off.
That's on.
There's the kick.
Just a little low.
Doesn't quite come off his foot.
And it's blocked.
Could have easily stayed on the park.
Okay.
Good work.
Let's get moving now.
From Kawa Tadze.
I'm going to put Tadze on the line.
He's got a little bit of a backhand.
I'm going to put time back on.
Okay.
Water off please.
Water off.
It's not actually an official water break here.
There's an injury.
Looks like the big man Francisco Fernandez at 38 years old.
Just getting a bit of treatment.
Maybe a tactical injury.
Stand in front of him mate.
Stand in front of him.
We've still got people on the field.
If ever was the old Kit Kat.
Take a break.
I think that's one of those.
I don't know what the part of his version is.
As you have seen, Martins.
That's cleaner from Portugal.
And it had to be.
Simoes.
Trucks up and sets the platform.
A match.
This time with all of his experience.
Finds a safe touch.
And that is much more like it.
From Portugal as they look to the edge of the 22.
Marching on post.
Portuguese fans have sensed that.
Matthew Carly hasn't taken a few more steps down the touch line before sticking his flag in the air.
Number is five.
Always something happening in a World Cup match.
The crowd have been great.
Going to take a match of charity.
George is one stop.
He's lifting up the meters.
Moving up Portuguese defenders with them.
Shadikadze for Abzandadze out the back.
Here's Todawha.
Here's Trouble.
This is Ninius feeling the hot stepper.
Well, cut down by Portela again.
Portugal pinch it again.
Oh, they're taking some big body blows.
Coming back with a few telling shots of their own, the Portuguese.
Yeah, again, they've just given up that gain line.
But they've done enough to get hands over it.
It's the Georgians who aren't getting enough bodies out wide to secure the ruckball.
I didn't see anything, but I'll have a look.
The two big 13s collided midfield and it was Betancourt who was claiming there was some obstruction.
And there's the two sets of fans going at it.
Telling like a stat popped up on your screen there.
Seven visits to the Portuguese 22 by Georgia.
One by Portugal and that line out throws crickets.
Option men, Scrum all on out.
Scrum.
Scrum called.
Here's Emma.
Scrum called should be a t-shirt, I reckon, for Georgia.
That'd do well.
Both sides.
You control your side, they control theirs.
And there's some French up in royalty.
Gael Ermey, captain of the French women's team.
Très chic, Gael, with those sunglasses.
Très chic, indeed.
Here to enjoy the rugby and to lose.
Getting ready for WXV, the inaugural World Championship.
Three levels for the women.
Her team will be down playing the world champion, Black Ferns, on October 21st down in New Zealand.
So much excitement around that.
I know Canada and England are playing today in Exeter with preparation.
Oh!
Great that Rugby is giving those women a chance to measure themselves every year.
What a platform this is for Georgia.
And again, we're going to have the Saturday night first receiver,
Klesilanti, with the miss pass to Todiwap,
who sits down, Nuno Suzakic.
And then is getting tackled into touch by a pack of Portuguese wolves.
Well, there's some real emotions and afters there.
Big collision.
Little help from his teammates.
Did Malta.
As they go wide here.
Maybe the old advice, miss pass.
He comes up, Malta gets dropped down, but then the boys come in and help him out.
He was touched by White.
It's a red throw.
Big hit there.
Ball down.
There's actually going to be a Georgian throw in here because
Xandrothodiwap threw the ball off a Portuguese player.
He was touched by White first, guys.
Starts the red line out.
Again, the officials doing a good job to lock these things up.
Look at those tackles that Spaniard.
It just tells the story, doesn't it?
That's amazing.
That isn't necessarily taking his toll now, but it will do in the last 20 minutes,
last 30 minutes of this match.
Georgia continue to rule the Tudu skies.
And they will merrily sap the energy and the morale of the Portuguese players.
And proceeds to Characazze to Cresolazze.
Running short, running hard.
Committing defenders.
Abshandadze, Nini Ashvili is lurking again.
So is Tabudzadze.
Takes two to stop the man they call the bullets in Georgia.
Mabukashvili again.
Big carrying figures already for a lot of these Georgian forwards.
Here's Gorgadze.
Better shot from Simoish.
Onside.
Use it.
Here, Nini Ashvili.
Mabukashvili does likewise.
Seven phases now for Georgia.
Mikhail Tadze.
Close to 130kg on the hoof.
Characazze the captain, Cresolazze.
He'll be obstructing them, but the penalty goes Georgia's way.
White.
13, White was offside first.
Yeah, it looks like there's initially an offside.
But it's still a very close game.
13, White was offside first.
Yeah, it looks like there's initially an offside call.
And then the obstruction meant the play stops at that point too.
Already, Hitenkor has been involved in a lot here, but he was up too quick from that previous run.
Offside.
The numbers offside.
13, never onside.
13.
Okay.
That's fair to be an officiating from Paul Williams.
There was an obstruction.
Because we were playing advantage to Georgia, the first offence was a Portuguese one.
And Georgia going to go for the costs.
And that is Betancourt, he's deemed to be outside.
He's looking up at the big screen and agreeing with the Portuguese fans who are whistling.
He didn't like it Rob.
So earlier, you were very close to crossing over here.
Referees having a bit of a conversation around these decoy lines.
Very clearly. So just tidy that up please.
I think it's right, it's just tidying it up. It's not a massive issue.
It happens all the time at all levels of rugby.
But if you're clearly obstructing the play, then it isn't fair.
You know, we see this at the moment with Portugal on the ropes.
You can see why they've gone for a 6-2 split on the bench.
Six forwards ready to come on.
Jannuap Shandadze chips his third kick of the match straight down the middle.
And at the moment it's the Georgia fans outnumbered in the stands.
But by far the happier of the two sets of supporters.
Well Rob, you talk about the bench which is such an important part in a fixture like this.
Georgia have gone 5-3. That is the dominance of their own forwards.
So contrary to maybe the South Africans or Portugal who's trying to shore things up.
They've got a few extra backs they can call them.
Shachamitian again, he was being impetuous.
One year.
Use it!
No, use it now!
He wanted one more meaty Georgian lump for protection.
Paul Williams telling him to get on with it.
Opel are cemented by Sandro Podoa.
Portugal try for a tackle in the air.
The officials are moved.
Match to Xerquera.
Oh no, it is a penalty advantage for tackle in the air.
You've got an advantage.
Tackle in the air.
Portugal move this.
Use the free-flowing backs in their midst.
There's one of the best, Rodrigo Mata.
Match innovative.
Portela uses his height to gather it back in.
Another penalty advantage.
Lada White jerseys off to the right.
They go left instead.
Tomas Appleton the captain.
Oh, he sits down.
Nariashvili.
Portela.
Break over that pure for Portugal.
Xerquera.
Tagher.
Storty.
He's far as right.
Storty's away!
Can Nariashvili catch him?
No, he can't!
Portugal rocking beneath a flurry of Georgian punches.
Had rallied and landed a belter of their own.
And this place has erupted.
Well, this is what Portugal bring.
Rafael is starting back to the sub.
But look at the hands of the big men.
Quick passes.
Great recognition to skip it out wide.
Quick ball, get it to the man, the danger man.
He stops and cuts right inside.
Overchase from the Georgians.
And Storty had just enough to get in the corner.
Check out this.
Mike Tagher.
He pushes him through the gap.
That's an assist if ever you've seen one.
What a combination of power and pace.
Do I get fantasy points for that?
It's an assist.
Some well-matched.
Missed three kicks off the tee against Wales.
He was nursing a calf problem last weekend.
He says he's over that.
This is about as tough a kick as it's possible to face.
It's curling back.
It's off the post.
Unlucky Samwell match.
13-5 it remains.
Yeah, only the five in the end, but what a crucial, crucial score.
Five minutes left in the half to give the lift.
He cuts back and he finds a massive hole.
Again, the Georgians just overchase.
They weren't connected.
Huge lift.
You can see the joy in the Portuguese players.
They've had a tough first half defending for long periods, Rob.
But that's their return.
That's their first shot and they landed a hell of a punch.
There's the try score of Storty.
Off he goes again.
He's got the pace to really stretch this Georgian defense.
You need the accuracy in those close quarter exchanges.
Suzygetch, look at this.
Oh my goodness, Suzygetch has split them open.
Storty's on his bike.
Kvasseladze and Nini Ashvili mop things up well.
And now Nini Ashvili returns the compliment.
And he finds Sharikadze,
Chachanidze, all the big boys getting involved.
Giga Ashvili, great pass to Mamouk Ashvili.
Oh, his clasp of Fernandes.
Oh, it's like a scene from Jurassic Park.
And there's a penalty advantage being played as Georgia play on.
Nini Ashvili straightens, cuts beyond Appleton.
Akrasidze on his shoulder.
This is incredible rugby.
It's breathless from both teams.
Sharikadze gets on it again.
And we're going to have to stop because we're just too close to Shalva Mamouk Ashvili.
And we're going to have a lot of footage to pull over here.
It was a no-arms tackle.
No-arms tackle from Francisco Fernandes on Shalva Mamouk Ashvili.
So Paul, I want to show you the actions of number one white.
It's a high tackle and there's no attempt to wrap also.
That's the voice of Joy Neville, our television match official.
And you want to see the tackle.
The big man, what a hit it was.
But they're looking to see if he wrapped his arms and if it's indeed a high tackle.
It was a massive hit.
It was a collision. It wasn't a tackle.
It looks really bad.
He's obliged to open his arms there.
And hold on.
Well, there's head-to-head contact as well.
Clearly no attempt to wrap it.
That's unacceptable.
Yeah.
It was white one, mausoleum Joy.
Yes, number one white.
Okay.
Come on.
Number one.
Just let me deal with this and then I'll come back to you, okay?
So clearly no wrapping the tackle.
It's dangerous.
It's the yellow card threshold.
Yes.
It's the yellow card.
We were going to tackle the guy.
But as soon as he was lifting, there was a...
Francisco Fernandes.
Obviously, it's the yellow card.
We've got the Fulham player, a view official, who has eight minutes now to assess all the angles.
Decided whether to upgrade that challenge to a red card.
Okay, Portugal, we're going to put time back on.
The blue card is yellow.
Just behind the kicker, please, men.
I think a key element as we look back at this video is the head contact.
That does raise the level.
It's going to be a penalty to Georgia.
Just a couple of minutes left here in the first half.
Yeah, there's a clear framework that the officials will work through.
Our Fulham player, the official, will assess whether there was head contact,
whether it was foul play, if the player was at fault.
And determine the degree of danger, whether it's a yellow or a red card.
And then look to apply any mitigation, if there's any to be applied.
Such as a drop in height or a late change in direction from Shalva Mamoukashvili.
I would suggest it will be a very nervous few minutes for Francisco Fernandes and for Portugal.
The pack is on the back foot and they've just lost one of their biggest beasts.
Chachanidze gathers for Georgia.
And against the sediment in Portugal, Georgia on the move.
Penalty advantage.
Paul Williams is thinking yellow card again here.
Saki Nadze gets to within a few meters.
Apracite.
Now they go wide.
Abshan Dadze's kick for Tabutsadze.
It's just a touch and go, but he knew he had that penalty.
I was going to say, if you're new to rugby, you knew he had advantage.
So the referee is giving him a shot here.
This is when it goes down.
And they thought they tried the high risk option.
It wasn't on the pass, so he tried the kick, knowing he could come back.
And have a very good attacking position from the penalty.
Mike, that was you collapsing.
There's your mark.
All day, mate.
What will Georgia do here?
What are we doing?
Portugal down a prop.
Discipline. Discipline.
Discipline.
With that man in the bin, obviously they don't have to replace him because it's a line-up.
Had it been a scrum, you need a specialist player in there.
I'm surprised they maybe didn't choose that for that reason.
Look at all the subs in the dead ball area, just looking, urging on their team to drive this one over.
These feel like very significant moments in this Rugby World Cup pool C showdown.
Portugal cling on Manfuli.
Keep it up. Keep it up.
Georgia drive forwards.
Down by Red.
Where's the ball?
But he felt those giants somewhere.
One, two, three.
And they'll have a goal line drop-out.
Short first and then held up over the line.
I'm not really sure why they took the line-up there because essentially they tried to form a scrum anyway, the drive in wall.
So the referees adjudicated that it was brought down by Red, they came down on their own and then they went over the line but it was held up off the ground.
So that would give a goal line 22-3.
And then they're going to have a goal line drop-out.
The referees adjudicated that it was brought down by Red, they came down on their own and then they went over the line but it was held up off the ground.
So that would give a goal line 22-meter drop-out for the Portuguese to try and get some reprieve here.
Just 30 seconds left in this first half.
Lach, what's it wrong?
I think I've got the gags there.
Reloads for Georgia.
A try before half-time.
Could be so sweet and so important for Georgia.
Tackle narrow!
By the same token, keeping them out.
The Portuguese.
Oh, there's Ninias Filho again.
He's cut the masunder.
Chachanitse for Apra Sitte.
And he was just in touch as he formed it on the inside.
David Ninias Filho is a one-man assassin right now as far as the Portuguese defence are concerned.
Well they got the move they wanted, they found the hole, they've looked at this on tape, the inside ball.
Unfortunately it's Chachanitse, the man is put away.
He turns around and immediately looks for more speedy help.
He's a bit too late there.
Credit to Scrum Half getting it across.
Marques has been fighting the whole half here.
The two meerkats going at it again.
That's the best description of Scrum House ever from you, Jamie.
Portugal just want this ball off the pitch.
The clock is red, Marks checks.
And Marks, gratefully, gives his team a breather.
They are clinging on in there, the Portuguese.
They kick off this immense second half.
So much at stake for these two long-time rivals of course in Munich.
But so much more than that with fight for points in this Rugby World Cup pool.
Third place in the group guarantees automatic qualification for Australia 2027.
Georgia will have come into this with designs on the quarterfinals top two finish.
And Jamie, great news there for the Portuguese.
Not only is Fernandes able to return, the contact wasn't around the head area.
But with Georgia having 67% possession and only putting 13 points on the board.
For Patrick Laziskaya, the head coach, there's a lot of positive to take at that halftime.
To see if Portugal can build on that.
As you go straight over the top, Appleton couldn't take it.
Portela could.
Madeira, missed last weekend's lost to Wales.
Put that in the warm-up for injury.
Serkera, there's that trademark off-road basketball style.
In the six-week-time lock, with Donkua.
Whirling his way through two tackles.
And then losing the ball on the floor.
Just a little knock on there. Frustrating.
Just looking a little disorganized there as they built that attack.
They're all going to have to be on the same page.
And now again, Laziskaya talked about this is the first time he's really had all his players together.
And so many of them playing in French clubs.
They don't get released and they don't have a lot of games together.
So this is a luxury and I want to make history here.
This is the first club since Francisco Fernandes was sinned in.
So Portugal must now bring on a frontal replacement.
And it will be W. Quistar wearing 60.
Normally a jersey reserved for the replacement hooker, but Portuguese do things a bit differently.
There is Mr. Quistar.
And off.
It's going to come in there loose forwards.
It's Joel Granate who they've sacrificed.
Tactically, really a bit shocked by Georgia's option before not to take a scrum rather than the line-up from the penalty.
Because bringing on that extra foot roller now means they lose a back roller.
And in phase play, back rows are usually a bit more handy than the front rowers.
So no dissent credit to the front row union.
But certainly interesting tactics from Georgia.
Yeah, great point. A full six minutes.
Portugal without having to bring on that front row man.
Keep it up.
Take it out.
Quistar under pressure.
Ball is available for Gazzet.
He spins away to the left.
Absham Gazzet to his captain Shadi Gazzet.
Nice shot from Pedro Butancura.
That is much more like it from the Portuguese defence.
They've been under so much pressure in the first half.
And that was better. More aggressive defence.
Pedro Butancura just supplying himself.
Perfect timing as the pass comes in.
Right there. Knocks the arm.
Thank you, sir.
He's done a lot of good things, Butancura.
Get up Shadi Gazzet.
Great come down.
Thomas Manic figure for Georgia.
50th time as captain.
Better line-up from Portugal to Martins.
And Portela off to Butancura.
And now here's Suzygec.
Marta running at Tabut Sadzi who clings onto him
and drags him just onto the white piece of the touchline.
Well, Wyn plays a little bit different than he used to be.
He gets that wide ball not a lot on.
He was trying to stay on the park.
Does just enough and then his hand goes over the line right there.
And that's the turnover.
That's poor attack from a team who love to attack.
If you have a short line-up, it means your big runners can be out wide
and make some inroads.
He was just checked passing, didn't really threaten
and as a result ran into touch.
Portugal need to improve from that.
Georgia lost three liners against Australia.
Perfect thus far.
And they set each department.
Martins has got way through on the middle of that ball.
Martins, he's helping Georgia backwards.
They have to play this.
The catch.
That is superb mall defence from Portugal.
And Nicola Martins in the orange scrum cap.
It is vintage mall disruption.
Turn over.
Yeah, if you're new to rugby, a mall is when the ball's off the ground.
No tackle is complete here.
And once they form up this mall and try pushing forward,
they have to use the ball when the referee says it.
But look at the big number seven swimming through there.
Nicola Martins does just enough.
Look at him, just competing all the way.
Because they can't get to ground,
Radjuskay and the coaches can celebrate,
it will be a Portugal put in.
Such a good player for the lead against the Welsh.
Nicola Martins, a try scorer,
joint top tackle with 14.
He makes more dominant tackles,
a tackle that forces your opponent backwards
than any other player in the Portuguese side.
Unfortunately, the reward of a scrum
is like a lupacol to Christmas.
Georgia will be living this.
They'll be happy with the reset too,
as that yellow box on the left of your screen
is ticking away just over a minute for Fernandes to come back.
Catch!
Boy!
Set!
So the Portuguese scrum does enough.
Casimo ish can play away,
trying to go over the top of Aposizu,
who goes onto a giant limp.
Cadera, maybe up to ten tackles without the ball.
Looking to make an impact with it.
March changes direction.
Patera straightening.
Can't pierce between the big Georgian forwards.
March again to push that.
Georgian nuts on that, but illegally so.
Penalty advantage Portugal.
March to Madeira, who's slaloming past defenders.
Quick ball for March again.
Portela sees a gap, he's come right.
But Chachanize, he keeps the ball alive.
This is put on court.
Suza gets to the outside.
Sturtees rubber.
Abshan Dantze traps it back well.
And they'll go back for the second of those penalty advantages.
Chachanize's high tackle.
And Francisco Fernandes prepares to re-enter the pitch.
High tackle.
Can't wait to get back out there.
It's a penalty for the high tackle.
But deceptive.
And how about Portela, just finding half-gaps in this Georgian defence.
He gets high tackled here, and this could be a yell.
The rest may have a look.
The crowd are going to let them know what they think.
What are we doing?
Shot a goal.
And they've taken their option to kick it goal.
And Rob, this place is going to heat up.
The big man gets to come back on.
And this goes over.
Just a five-point deficit for the Portuguese.
Typically like a boxing match where someone's been on the ropes.
Everyone in the crowd wants to see the uproar.
Nice to see smiles on faces.
It's very much about Portugal now grabbing hold of an opportunity
and getting points back on the board.
A little glimpse of the Francisco Fernandes fan club there.
There's a section of Portuguese support with Fernandes face masks.
Might have been taking them off and hiding them a few minutes ago,
but they can enjoy the big fella's return.
So of course they're off.
Joel Granati, who was sacrificed on.
Francisco Fernandes back with us.
This kick to cut the gap to five.
March nails it.
Georgia 13, Portugal 8.
We have a game on our hands, ladies and gentlemen.
Wow, they've been hanging around.
There'll be some questions being asked with the Georgians.
We'll see how they respond here.
Will Scrum Half is doing well today.
Bad mistake from Javier Restorti.
A stunning score.
Hosted Portugal back into the scale.
Lach.
Fusilois.
I was happy there to make that run.
Holding now.
Chaser.
Chaser on.
Low trajectory on that kick from Lach.
Skipped alive.
And Sandro Dorua, the veteran.
Still got plenty of pep in his step.
36 and he then works under Dorua.
That's it.
Flat to Jalachonia.
And Prasidze comes round the corner.
Tabouj Sadzi.
Caught well by Rodrigo Marta.
I thought he'd stolen it.
He hadn't.
Jalachonia.
Abshan Dadzi.
This is such important throws.
Georgia look to reestablish momentum.
Haven't lost to Portugal in 18 matches.
15 wins, three draws.
Prosted.
Marks big shots.
Huge counter-rock comes in and Marks steals it.
And Suzygec.
Alonis Bess in front of him.
He's running it forward Suzygec.
Onto Matanj.
The stadium on its feet.
Here's Appleton the captain.
Cutting inside to within five meters.
Portugal flick the switch.
And now Georgia taking heavy fire.
Granate.
Now.
Marks.
Stibi Serkera.
Almost seven feet of Stibi Serkera.
And now.
Marks again.
Simoes.
Cut straight away from the tacklers.
You can feel the atmosphere change.
You can feel the Portuguese begin to dream.
Marta can't take it.
That precedes a hoops it away.
But Portugal will have a line-out.
Just outside the Georgia 22.
How a match can change.
How momentum can shift.
A huge shift as you say they had possession.
Look at the counter-rock.
From the Portuguese boys.
And this Georgian defense is starting to fall apart.
They've only made 42 tackles but they've missed 12.
So one in four tackles is missed.
And they're lucky out here.
The skipper decided to keep it.
I wonder if he could have given it outside.
Just five meters short.
But that's been the story for me as some of the subs start to come on here.
Rob.
The Georgia just falling off tackles out there.
It's like a rookie film.
Toot and fro when possession comes through.
Just that tempo change from Portugal is incredible.
Here's Marta.
He's a jack in the box.
Kigash really hauls him down.
What ground he made.
Another penalty advantage Portugal.
Marks around the fringes.
The veteran hooker.
Marks again.
Hasper Gaila.
Portugal with the wind in their sails.
With the try line tantalizingly close.
And with the penalty advantage up their sleeve.
There's the pasti granate.
That cleave Georgia open.
Two meters out now.
Marks.
Appleton.
Dabbing. Straightening.
Another penalty advantage.
Falls out.
Got the advantage.
Portugal hold on.
Opportunity knocks.
For Los Lobos.
And everybody inside
knows it.
Four penalty advantage.
Numbers out wide.
Susa Getsch.
The pass goes behind Storti.
If it went in front of him.
He had an untrue path to the line.
Any indication what Lajusky
wants him to do here?
The coach has loaded a message for three points.
We've had a couple of quick penalties
inside the 22k.
It's an official warning. You need to pass that message on now.
Next one goes.
Clear message.
Come in up Shari Khan.
Georgia.
Another infringement down here.
It's a yellow card.
Portugal are going to take three points here.
Well the last pass aside.
That is top class attacking rugby.
From the Portuguese team.
Brilliantly they're backing themselves.
Putting it out the back door. This last pass doesn't go to hand.
But up to that point.
Outstanding play. Into play between
backs and forwards.
Some would say
interesting decision here.
To go for the three points.
The problem is against Georgia.
You just can't guarantee your set piece.
Be it line or scrim. This is sensible.
Get your points when you're down there.
March bangs it over.
And suddenly.
It's a two point ball game.
On two occasions
the captain Thomas Appleton has backed himself.
And on two occasions he was brought down just short.
Wonderful
scenes in the stands.
These fans feel this is their day.
They feel history is at hand.
As Levan Maistashvili
goes to his bench again and brings on
Young Luka Makkava.
At fly half for Tere Wabshan.
That's it. Strong first half.
Keeping with most of his team.
A quieter start to the second.
Makkava can play. He's a good game manager.
And they want his
kick in and streaks marks in the contest.
Just under half an hour to play.
Okay, use the ball.
Holding.
Naturally.
So touch found.
34 years of age.
Some of the marks should be 35 in December.
He still has such
towering importance.
In this Portuguese squad.
All of his wisdom. All of his experience.
And of course his 82nd minute penalty.
That took Portugal
to the World Cup.
Defeating the USA.
It's coming twice.
Well the kick in game we thought would be a bigger factor.
But both teams are playing with ball in hand.
It works out for Georgia.
Portugal have stolen it again.
Jose Madero this time.
Another important breakdown.
Jackal.
And Portela flings it wide.
Appleton.
Can they create more magic?
Put on core.
Two man tackle.
Tabutsadze and Kofisa Lazy in there quickly.
And the first half.
And the second half.
And Tabutsadze in there quickly.
Use it.
A long way to get to that breakdown.
Fernandes.
Rebecca and back in amongst it.
Holding both sides.
Three.
Into the air.
I don't see much of William Ashvili in this second half.
Red holding him.
Slaps it downfield.
And it's in.
Virtually no kick chase from the Georgians.
Sorry Jamie but that's it's side.
It's just now going to go dead.
It is.
And that's a big yardage game for Georgia.
They'll have the scrum back from where
Portela kicked it.
And you can see much of it.
Portela makes of that.
And Rob I don't know what you're picking up there.
As they see some fresh legs and we know why.
There's a lot of Georgian forwards walking around this park at the moment.
There's a lot of forwards generally looking pretty tired here.
We see substitutes are made to exactly
repair what we're seeing.
And the exhaustion from that first
40 minutes is showing on both sides of the field.
Special moment for the man wearing
number 19 today.
No doubt Che Ashvili.
Big sheathed head in the middle of that Georgian scrum.
It's his 50th cap today.
He's come on for him.
Fingy Zampter adds it on as well.
For Shabnam Amakashvili.
And that is the end of the game for
Shabnam Amakashvili.
Big man, big character.
Pitch support here to
Ronevon.
And that he pushed up.
Ronevon might be with us for the duration.
Back to more comfortable territory.
The great shot from the cable can.
It's the drone but scrum time for Georgia.
They can build something from this.
Set!
Vasite for Tabudzadeh
again off his wing.
Here's Makaava, clattered right by
Hidrobutankur.
Ronevon Ashvili,
looking at most of a difficult situation.
Gets the hands free
and pops it off beautifully.
Oh, a steal!
Pinch back.
These wolves of Portugal
hunting
and stealing.
And mischief
making with this Georgian attack.
Toudoua rattles it high.
Rattles it out on the full.
The most experienced back on the pitch
makes a big error.
Well, everything's going Portugal's way.
The contact here, watch the big number four
coming in, said I'll have some of that.
Jose Madeira! And those are the things
that are making a difference right now.
Just like this kick that's gone straight into touch.
Watched all the way by Mouros Uzegich.
One of those inspired by
the great 2007 vintage.
Portugal have never won a Rugby World
Cup match.
They haven't beaten Georgia
in 15 years.
March.
They'll tell that. New options, he doesn't need any.
What a pass inside!
Stalked his away! Oh, he's gone!
Stalked his in for a double!
Portugal have risen from the ashes!
From bleak in the
first half, to blistering
in the second.
Rafael Storti doubles up.
And this is a
World Cup classic.
Well, the ball was balled initially.
But Portela, who's been for me, the man,
the thorn in the side of the Georgians,
gets it to the pace, man. And Storti's
looks to set up the fullback. Actually, it's the
blind winger, Tadua, and he just falls down.
Can't believe his luck. Watch
as he squares up here.
The last defender falls on the ground.
And Storti has a run in for a second.
He wasn't picked last weekend.
Fans saw Pinto go ahead of him.
Pinto might have played today
if he hadn't been suspended.
And no match
to stretch the Portuguese leads.
No problem.
Amazing.
From 13
mil down,
they lead 18-13.
Well,
Markson and Portela
in the 9 and 10 jersey are dominating.
They're winning this battle.
Storti's getting the reward.
Look at the
passion.
And not the last time
you're going to be hearing Rafael Storti
scoring some rogues.
The young man, 22 years old, getting celebrated
by the oldest boy, 38.
Fantastic for Portugal.
Rafael Storti was named
Francisco Fernandes, made his Portugal debut
in 2010.
A lot of big
George and penalty there.
Portugal holding on.
That's a huge call.
Portugal had their hands on
the penalty. You know what this means, Rob?
Kick down the line.
Line out. Pressure from the forwards.
This is where the forwards
are really going to have to step up for
Georgia. They love going forward.
They love driving line-ups. This is very much
something they're going to grab
and mold into what is
a Georgian masterpiece.
She loves it.
First throw for
Dungas Zantaradze.
Well, Martins got hands to it.
Who wants this match ball?
Portugal do.
Last fine.
And suddenly all the things that were going well for Georgia,
swimmingly well in the first half,
are threatening to implode
in the second.
Easy.
Another Georgian penalty.
Portugal off their feet.
Hugo Hasfahegar
straight to ground, wearing three.
Sailing straight off.
So the call is
the arriving Portuguese players
aren't holding their weight, they're sealing it off.
To me a tough call.
Here they go. Here we go Georgia.
Desperate for some momentum
and some tries. And have they got it down?
No.
That's incredible.
Last ditch defence.
It's heroic from Portugal.
Becker Gorganzi, turned turtle.
Over the Portuguese line.
It's a goal on drop out.
It's Petancourt.
What a play, what a play.
Well,
one of the best scrums in the tournament, they turned down the five meter scrum.
It's a well-worked play.
But Petancourt has the presence of mind.
Get on the ball. What a drop out.
Max chases Nuno Esquivel away back into his own half.
Oka Red.
Nuno Esquivel sends it skywards.
It's won by Portugal.
Martins has pause on it.
Pick up that is for Max.
He feeds on to Saqueira.
And this is where Portugal can play.
This is where they can
drive daggers
into opposition teams.
When the game opens up.
When it gets fast and loose.
Los Lobos are on the prowl.
Appleton, the captain,
a dentist back home in Lisbon.
Now on the cusp of leading
his men to a first ever
Rugby World Cup win.
The match takes the sting out of things.
Marta chases after it.
What a catch from Marta.
He's got support with him. Saqueira leaves it
to Taggier.
Rodrigo Marta, king of the Toulouse skies.
Everything going with Portugal right now.
Portela sends it wide.
March. Appleton.
Finding the warm embrace of Jose
Madeira but is caught behind the game line.
George up quickly.
March.
Domine the kick going instead to Appleton.
She's again shot in the back.
This is Marta again.
Portugal's record
triscorer.
Incredible.
30 tries.
Here they come again.
This is Thibaut de Freitas.
It's on. There's numbers.
Portela. Plenty of white
jerseys away here.
This is Bretoncourt straightening and
fending off Gorgazza who holds on.
Use it!
No scrimmage here.
Much involved in that breakdown.
I can't take the roll.
Portela puts the cross kick in.
Marta's after it.
Tabushadze takes it really well.
That's a magnificent
catch under huge
huge jerseys.
Wow, there's some
breeze running around. Is it
concern that maybe he's milking this a little bit?
He's definitely contacted in the air.
It's a great take as you said.
The pace of this game.
Still 18 minutes to play.
We can play.
Really good take.
He does get hit in the air. That's the penalty.
Mark's up there.
Guys, back to 10 minutes.
Here's our mark here.
And it's a penalty.
It's a penalty.
And Rizzi just nailed it.
The game play now for the next 18 minutes
has to be at a lower tempo.
They cannot sustain this level
of pace across the pitch. You can see much.
He's absolutely spent as a scrimmage
because he's doing all the wits.
It's about using that pace and extra
gear that Portugal clearly have at the right
times. And Georgia
needs to keep grinding.
Georgia up to 20 missed tackles.
And the possession stats. 53 for
Georgia. That was 67.
Now Portugal with 47% of the ball.
What's happening?
A tale of two hearts.
A tale of two latex as well.
Portugal just fumbled after.
Running it back.
Portela.
A bit of soccerista style.
Suza Ghech.
With the hitch kick. Taking on Shere Khanzeh.
But Onkur with him.
Yeah, got to his feet.
But got up, went again.
OK, news now.
Portugal
into that attacking shape.
That's Ferreira.
What's loose.
And it has gone forwards.
And perhaps Portugal trying to play a little too much rugby.
Well this game's on a knife edge.
I'm not sure because there's so many
holes out wide. When they
stretch the Georgians, they're not connected out
there. This one just bobbles as he
looks to offload. Not sure
they did go forward.
And that's their game plan. You see 15
offloads, the third most in their last
poor game. Portugal love to play expansive
rugby. We're not saying don't.
Just don't try and do it every single phase.
They've got that shift change. Pick your
moment and play for it.
When we talk about the French flair, we've seen
a heck of a lot of Portuguese flair here.
Lazio Scherz influence.
The fact that these players are playing their rugby in France.
They've always been a dangerous side
Portugal and willing to back themselves.
We keep going.
Thank you.
And Georgia with
full body, fresh legs down there.
Can they affect this, change this
tide that is rolling Portugal's
way at the moment? Guys, please stand. I think
that gap is far too big. Far too big.
We're just going to go straight down there.
Please reset. They just look
too big.
Less subs on for Portugal as you'd
expect because the boys on there are doing
the job. They're up by five
looking for their first ever Rugby World Cup
win.
The two moments where you'd think that Georgia would have gone for
the scrums, they haven't.
The line-up is subsequently the tap five meters
out. This is their
bedrock. This is their foundation for everything. They need
to be seeing the scrum as a sanctuary.
Thomas Sarge stays right in behind
that scrum. Let's see where he goes.
The second of the shot comes in from Portugal
and they win the penalty.
Back and down.
Far side.
Well, you don't see that every day.
The Georgian scrum, the nudge
comes from there. They're the ones
who are penalised for taking it down.
We'll do it at the line-up. That's the Portuguese five row and
the tight five are doing their job.
Yeah. Full penalty.
Yeah.
The visceral joy
writ large on the face of Samuel Nudge.
It was the task of
probing Portugal into
the Georgian 22.
Portugal bring on another substitution.
Martin Bello
is on for the giant Stevie Serkera.
Well, how about the
34-year-old Mike Tadjim?
This is clubbing at Pepinho on the
hooker. Portugal still in there.
Still throwing this line-up.
Wilt Aplanzi winning 23, trotting on
for Sandro Todoa.
Oh, he's there.
Sorry.
Are we good to go?
He's off the back there now.
Time back on.
Into this
engrossing encounter
and overthrowing the line-out.
Appleton picks up
the pieces. Portugal
10 metres out.
Here's Matinsh.
Backwards.
What a booster other try would give Portugal.
How close they are
to achieving
the unprecedented.
Madera's carry.
March.
De Freitas.
Portugal making meters
with each carry.
There's the Bullocking carry from Bello.
March to Portela.
Marta's off his wing.
Marta's causing mayhem.
Scorty rescues it back
with a rouser knock on Mayer.
Better red player, guys.
Well, the call is knock-on on the field.
Portugal's so comfortable on the ball,
going through the phases.
Here, as he looks to offload,
does he squirt out of his hand?
Maybe a red hand on it.
It's not going to matter.
Can you move over here, though?
It looks like Marques, the scram-hound,
is grabbing up.
No, no, over here. I'm going to set the scram up.
No, here's our Marques.
No, no, no, no. Off, off.
Every single decision made here
is pivotal.
The tension around this stadium is palpable.
Shoulder out, please.
Good.
Oh, this is what rugby World Cups are all about.
We're here to lose.
12 minutes to play.
Fine.
Free kick, Georgia.
No way.
Close, Mike Tazsia. No way, sir.
Spice and balance like we spoke about.
Jilted front rowers around the rugby World.
Kader bangs Georgia downfields.
And they have some respite
from this Portuguese onslaught.
That's a great kick.
The forwards will like that. Looking for fresh legs.
Oh, on comes
Big Lerl Campa.
Big.
I think it's rugby anarcho show.
He is retiring
after the Rugby World Cup.
35 year old Hooper is on from Mike Tazsia.
Time on.
Over.
His first throw is a good one.
The noise inside this stadium is quite incredible.
It might get louder in a few minutes time.
As Marta gets away from Kvisiladze.
She's a gitch to Max
at first receiver.
Close from Campa to Betancur.
Here's Storti.
Here come Portugal. Is this their moment?
Not quite yet.
And Georgia scroung Storti into touch.
Georgia dangling by a threat here.
Well credit the Georgians for making the desperation tackle here.
But the movement and the work
off the ball by the Portuguese players.
Portuguese players
constantly asking questions.
Again Storti lucky for the hat trick.
Does he get pulled in the touch?
Foot just hits the line there.
Nice work from the official.
Frustrated Portuguese fans.
Beka Sakurati has been replaced by
Jogi Tsutsukurite.
From the Georgian backboard.
What pressure on this throw now.
Portuguese voices
ringing in Zantharadze's ears.
And he gets the money shot over the top.
Beka Gorgadze.
Jorginho back to
Kava.
It's a good feeling.
But again Portugal are
really want to be.
Got a feel for the fans on the
far side of the stadium to the right.
Because they've seen their rugby. All the action has been
down in this quarter.
Georgia first half. Now Portugal
the second. Georgia without scoring
a point in the second half so far.
Over the top again. But Appleton again is there.
The captain puts his body on
the line to ensure it's Portuguese
possession. Into the final
ten minutes now.
Five point game. Match.
Away for Wallace.
David Wallace.
Takes two down the front.
Washed up.
March. There's a gap there.
March finds some support to
plunder through it.
Big penalty Georgia
again. That's important.
Goren Papite
with the beard.
March and
two minds there.
And he hit
Campos. He didn't really want it and he got double
tackled. So perhaps a chance
for the Georgians to swing them over to Nick.
Gains some territory.
Back to set piece. The loss at
piece didn't function and the ball was stolen.
That's the double tackle.
A little slow to arrive.
Where's the Portuguese support?
No, no, no, no. Don't quit.
Right where you are.
Roger Laneh goes to plan.
To pull this from the fire.
Shaddy Katzen.
A tireless skipper.
Carries into the teeth of the Georgian
Portuguese defense.
Chris Eladze.
Oh, then a knock on.
Fumbled forward by
Demurta Pladze.
As Chris Eladze shoveled the ball back to him.
And every
mistake, every
Georgian infringement
was greeted by the most
raucous of cries.
The Portuguese support.
And there's going to be a big cheer here
because Samuel March
who's been so
brilliant for Portugal
is about to get a place by Pedro
Lukas.
Well, hasn't he? March and Portela have been supreme.
They've won the battle of the halfbacks.
And the Georgians, a proud nation Rob, we know,
trying their hardest, but it's almost like
they're individuals out there at the moment.
And they're not putting any team play together.
It's just not clicking. You're exactly right.
It's not about them not scoring a point in the second half.
They've barely been down to Portuguese territory.
Some teams around the world spend
millions trying to get a scrum like
Georgians. As the warrior walks off,
the Georgian front five have to really
step up now. It's not about the glamorous backs,
it's about the forwards at front.
Confident hero
leaves the amphitheater.
But the battle is not yet won.
What a moment for young Pedro Lukas.
He's got to be a little bit more confident.
What a moment for young Pedro Lukas
in the 22 jerseys. Come on.
Scrum half, he's got eight minutes to play out
in what would be history for the
Portuguese.
Those statistics don't look
surprising, but the second half
portion of that is remarkable
from Portugal.
I was looking to be out there in Dubai when they had
their golden moment to qualify for this tournament.
They've built since then the strongest squad
they've ever assembled and their stats are backing it up.
They are fronting up here at the Ruby World Cup
in Portugal.
The service stats for meters made 600m
in the game by Portugal, over 500
of those gained in the second
half alone. How the tables
have turned.
And now this oscillating poo match
hangs in the balance.
Who can step up and be a hero for
their team?
David Wallace, who rescues the cheating
and soaks up the tackles.
Young Pedro Lukas, 22 years old.
Draws an offside penalty.
George up too quickly.
Portugal can gamble here with
Suza Ghej. Lukas as well offside.
22's in front, clearly.
22's in front of the kick.
Can't chase a kick if you're in front of the
guy who kicked it. Offside.
And you know what, in many ways they want this penalty.
The clock is ticking through this.
22. Offside.
The player was offside.
It was Kava.
So a chance for Portugal to slow it down.
Oh sorry. It was 20.
2-0.
Suza Ghej
propels Portugal into
Georgian territory.
And Rob, I know that Portuguese fans
are tasting this, but turn around right behind you.
There is a mass of kids going.
Absolutely ballistic because you think they're going to witness
history here.
And it is historical, and it's also games and shit.
Portuguese walk into this line-up. This is about
tempo. They don't have to win this game.
They just don't want to lose it.
Portugal can almost taste
a made in World Cup win.
Here's Pedro
Butancur, who's carried like a
bull all afternoon.
Appleton, Portela,
Marta. Oh, he's clattered.
Absolutely
marmalised.
Now the ball is loose.
Mavid Wallace.
Okay, okay, leave now.
Portela
sends it high.
Tabutsadze keeps it in.
Against Martins.
Tabutsadze wrapped up.
Lopes Janice.
Chase, on his 50th.
Jordan
tried to draw, a converted try to
win this.
Maccava, what hands.
Lopes Janice.
Big Guru and
Papidze, chundling into Martins.
Five minutes of this match left.
It's been a cracker.
Sun beats down.
One of those mighty backs down there.
Maccava
Logichashvili.
Chase feeling like
getting wrestles forward.
The phase is
mounting. The pressure building.
Here's Gorgaza, who's shed his
scrum cap.
No holds barred rugby now for Georgia.
As we enter the tenth phase of attack.
Maccava
Nini Ashvili.
They need a spark. Can Kviseladze
provide it?
Handed it on to Tabutsadze.
No knock on this time.
Between those two.
Guru and Papidze.
It's patient build up from the Georgians.
Is there a sting in the tail?
Maccava to Nini Ashvili.
Sharikadze.
Great ball into Gorgadze, who's
dummying and driving.
Sanaphonia.
Portugal putting bodies on the line.
Every man giving everything they have.
Sharikadze.
15 phases now.
The longest string of phases in this match.
Chachanidze makes it 16.
Nobzhanidze to Papidze.
Georgia's ball over to
Kviseladze.
It's a great ball.
Georgia's ball of attention supreme.
Can we find the killer touch?
Portugal do not want to
concede a penalty.
If discipline holds, will the
defence do likewise?
Kviseladze running the arc.
Sharikadze into Appleton.
Ball is not out.
Here's Olukas.
Leighton picked it up.
And might that be costly for Portugal?
Georgia can stick this in the corner.
It's not the kickable penalty that's a problem.
The ball is not beyond the line of thought.
Still on the right.
It is this line out.
Matkama.
Puts it right over the corner flag.
The Portuguese are inflamed by that.
They think it was
into touching goal.
The ball does go into touch.
In that final five metre.
The line out is taken on the five metre line.
They're happy it went into touch legally.
This is Georgia's time.
This is their go to play.
This is the forward brawn.
On which so many Georgian victories
have been constructed.
This is the forward brawn.
On which so many Georgian victories
have been constructed.
This is the forward brawn.
Have been constructed.
They trundle towards the corner flag.
They're over.
Didn't they get that ball down?
Georgia think they've scored here.
Let's listen to Paul Williams.
I don't have anything clear.
At this stage I've got nothing.
Yeah, Joy.
We are going to come to you with a
third question here unfortunately.
We don't have a clear grounding.
We don't have it clearly held up.
We've just got bodies everywhere.
So we need to establish a restart please.
Yeah, okay.
So off your decisions for our question.
Establishing restart, establishing whether
the ball has been grounded. Standby.
Thank you.
So it's all in the question. He doesn't have a clear grounding.
He doesn't have it clearly held up.
So the pressure is going to Joy Neville, the TMO.
And there's literally, there were
27 bodies in that pile up.
Is it on the line?
The line would be a try. Slowly.
We have it there in possession.
And has the ball
on the goal line.
So the decision is try.
The ball has successfully been grounded.
This try is going to stand.
And the scores will be level.
We do have clear footage of the ball being carried
and put on the line. So it is going to be a try.
Anguis Zantarance.
The unlikeliest of heroes for Georgia.
It's his sixth cap.
He has never started an international match.
He's given his team a chance
to win this game at the death.
Well there's the line up. This is as a result of the penalty.
Brilliantly taken.
And literally players are
running from every portion of the park.
There's 27 bodies involved.
Backs from both sides. But the Georgians do get it moving.
Looking for the line.
And he gets it to the line.
Great shot there from our crew.
They're going to break Portuguese hearts
with a huge, massive conversion to come.
Luka Matkava.
He kicked the winning
goal against Wales.
To ensure Georgia's first win over a tier one nation.
Away from home.
The whistles ring out.
Matkava
to give Georgia the leads.
From virtually on the left
touch line.
It's wide.
Matkava
misses from the left.
The scores are level and there is
time for a restart.
Wow.
It's all happening.
There's an HIA on the field just making sure the players
are OK after that massive
drive. We'll have the ball
reintroduced.
30 seconds to play. This game is not
over.
It is the most nerve
shredding of finales.
Final 15
seconds of play.
Portugal's giving for a penalty.
Oh, have they got one?
They have!
They were agonising
nanoseconds for Portugal.
As Paul Williams
slowly placed his whistle
in his mouth.
Now they have a shot to win
this game.
This time it's up.
Shot.
Shot called.
This was the take up.
He spins around and gets a bit
isolated.
The Portuguese forward.
They're right over the ball.
They've won the penalty.
I've got to say before this kick
is set up here, it's been an absolute
cauldron. A great credit to rugby.
But Paul Williams and his officiating team
have been superb under massive
pressures, taking their time
and just done a superb job officiating this
match. But right now, to know about
the match, we're going to have a look at
Daniel Gudesh and his right boot.
There will be people in this
stadium who cannot watch.
Samuel Marks, the first
choice kickers off.
81 minutes into the match.
Nuno Suzaguec
for history.
For Portugal's
first ever rugby
World Cup win.
It's wide!
It fades across the face.
And there is the full time whistle.
Everybody inside this stadium
rises to their feet,
son of wards.
And wherever you are,
wherever you're watching this,
we encourage you to do likewise.
Thank you.